Guide to the Braxton Craven Records and Papers, 1839-1882 UA.03.51.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Braxton Craven records and papers
1839-1882.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Craven, B. (Braxton), 1822-1882
UA.03.51.0001
9.2 Linear Feet
Braxton Craven (1822-1882) served as an administrator and educator during the nineteenth century evolution of Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.). Craven was Principal of Union Institute (1842-1851), President of Normal College (1851-1859), and President of Trinity College (1859-1863, 1866-1882). In addition, Craven actively participated in the Methodist Episcopal Church, South and the Order of the Masons in North Carolina. Collection includes correspondence, sermons and addresses, diaries, legal and financial papers, teaching materials, subject files, and photographs and portraits of Braxton Craven. Correspondents include John Wesley Alspaugh, Charles Force Deems, David Lowry Swain, David Settle Reid, Henry Toole Clark, and Calvin H. Wiley. Subjects include the Methodist Episcopal Church, college financial affairs, and the activities of the Trinity Guard, a unit of student-soldiers that Craven formed during the Civil War. English.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisitions Information
Received from multiple sources, including transfers from other campus units prior to the founding of University Archives:
No. 38-1528 received March 21, 1938.
No. 66-136 transferred from the Office of the Treasurer, August 3, 1966.
No. 78-54 transferred from the Craven-Pegram Papers in the Duke University Library, Manuscript Department, May 30, 1978.
No. 80-41 received May 1980.
No. 95-15 transferred from the vault of the East Duke Building, January 23, 1995.
No. 97-2 received by the Divinity School Library January 1997 and transferred to the Duke University Archives, February 6, 1997.
UA2008-0042 donation received June 22, 2008.
Biographical and Historical Note
Educator and Methodist clergyman, Braxton Craven was born in Randolph County, N.C., in 1822. Craven became licensed to preach in 1840, earned an A.B. (Hon.) in 1849 from Randolph-Macon College, and received various other degrees during his lifetime. His career included the following educational and administrative positions: Student-teacher, Union Institute (1841-1842); Principal of Union Institute (1842-1851); President of Normal College (1851-1859); President of Trinity College (1859-1863, 1866-1882). Braxton Craven died in 1882.
Duke University (Durham, N.C.) was established in 1924 and evolved from the following institutions: Brown's Schoolhouse (Randolph Co., N.C), 1838-1839; Union Institute (Randolph Co., N.C.), 1839-1851; Normal College (Randolph Co., N.C.), 1851-1859; Trinity College (Randolph Co., N.C.), 1859-1892 and (Durham, N.C.), 1892-1924).
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, student and financial records, reports, and other materials relating to the administration and academic program of Trinity College (Randolph Co., N.C.) as well as its predecessors, Union Institute and Normal College. Of particular interest are Braxton Craven's reports to the Board of Trustees, as well as minutes and resolutions of the trustees of Normal College, the constitution of Union Institute (1839), and Craven's correspondence with elected officials in North Carolina as well as Methodist clergymen. Individuals figuring prominently within the correspondence include trustee John Wesley Alspaugh; Charles Force Deems, a Methodist minister; David Lowry Swain, President of the University of North Carolina; North Carolina Governors David Settle Reid and Henry Toole Clark; and educator, Calvin H. Wiley. Subjects within the correspondence include the Methodist Episcopal Church, college financial affairs, and the activities of the Trinity Guard, a unit of student-soldiers that Craven formed during the Civil War. Some letters describe conditions and public sentiment in and around Randolph County during the Civil War. Also included are Craven's sermons and addresses, lecture notes, and diaries, as well as photographs of Craven.
Included are account books accounts of student tuition, bible, book, boarding fees, paper, and ink purchases. Several volumes include the signatures of students. Roll books contain students' names, courses, attendance, assignments, and grades. One volume contains accounting of women and children, and their amounts of bacon, meal, beef, and salt, that was possibly recorded during the Civil War.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; College presidents -- North Carolina; Randolph County (N.C.) -- History; Education -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Union Institute (Randolph County, N.C.); Wiley, Calvin Henderson, 1819-1887; Clark, Henry T. (Henry Toole), 1808-1874; Craven, B. (Braxton), 1822-1882; Reid, David Settle, 1813-1891; Normal College (Randolph County, N.C.); Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.); Swain, David L. (David Lowry), 1801-1868; Duke University -- History; Deems, Charles F. (Charles Force), 1820-1893; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- Clergy -- North Carolina; Freemasons -- North Carolina
- Correspondence, 1842-1882
  Arrangement note
  Arrangement: chronological
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence of Braxton Craven that survives documents the financial struggles of Normal College and later Trinity College. During the 1850s and 1860s, the correspondence describes attempts to gain state aid to the College and the formation of a cadet corps at Trinity. Included are typed copies from the original correspondence in the North Carolina Department of Archives and History in Raleigh, North Carolina. The Methodist Church seems to dominate the correspondence after 1859, when it becomes the chief financial supporter of the College. A few surviving family letters are also present. They pertain to the illness and death of Craven in 1882. Also included is a letterbook (1870-1882) that contains copies of letters, receipts, bylaws of the Trinity Normal School, bursar accounts, and faculty salary payments. Major correspondents include John Alspaugh, member of the Board of Trustees of Trinity College, Bishop Edward R. Ames of the Methodist Episcopal Church, Calvin Henderson Wiley, John S. Brown and Governors Thomas Settle Reid, David Lowry Swain and Henry Toole Clarke of North Carolina.
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
- Sermons, Speeches, and Addresses, 1841-1880
  Arrangement: alphabetical.
  Include sermons given by Craven at church services, commencements, and funerals. Some are incomplete or fragments of sermons. Also present are 14 volumes that contain drafts of sermons by Craven. The notebooks, mainly pocketsize, include Scriptural passages glued to pages, with handwritten exegeses beneath them.
  - All things are teachers, and all teaching is necessary (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anti-Christ (Box 1)
  - Asking but not recovering (Box 1)
  - The Atonement of Christ (Box 1)
  - Beauty Rebuked (Box 1)
  - Babes in Christ (Box 1)
  - Baccalaureate Sermon (Box 1)
  - Belief (Box 1)
  - Be ready (Box 1)
  - Besetting Sins (Box 1)
  - The Best Gifts (Box 1)
  - The Blood of Christ (Box 1)
  - Born Again (Box 1)
  - Brotherhood (Box 1)
  - Brotherly Love (Box 1)
  - The Christian Ideal (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Christian Kindness (Box 1)
  - Christian Life (Box 1)
  - Christian Manliness (Box 1)
  - The Christian's Prize (Box 1)
  - The Church (Box 1)
  - Christmas 1854 (Box 1)
  - The Church of God (Box 1)
  - Comfort Ye, My People (Box 1)
  - Conscience, a Test of Duty (Box 1)
  - Counting the Cost (Box 1)
  - Courage (Box 1)
  - Currency in God's Kingdom (Box 1)
  - Danger of missing heaven (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Day of Small Things (Box 1)
  - The Day of Trouble (Box 1)
  - Demonstrating the Heart (Box 1)
  - Denominationalism (Box 1)
  - Denouncing Sinners (Box 1)
  - Diversity in Unity (Box 1)
  - Divine Life (Box 1)
  - The Diving Omniscience (Box 1)
  - Doc's Religion Satisfy the Soul (Box 1)
  - Edification (Box 1)
  - The Effective Element of Christianity (Box 1)
  - Elegance and Durability of Christianity (Box 1)
  - The Emphatic Work of the Church (Box 1)
  - Enough Help Already Given (Box 1)
  - Equal Error of Sensationalism and Rationalism (Box 1)
  - Evangelism (Box 1)
  - Every Man needs a Pastor (Box 1)
  - The External Manifestations of God's People (Box 1)
  - The Fall and Atonement (Box 1)
  - Family Religion (Box 1)
  - The Father draweth them (Box 1)
  - Feeding and Governing the Flock (Box 1)
  - Final Destiny (Box 1)
  - The Fixed and Variable (Box 1)
  - The Friendship of the World (Box 1)
  - Fruits meet for Repentance (Box 1)
  - Given to Idols (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - God's Anger Turned Away (Box 1)
  - God's Graciousness to Penitents (Box 1)
  - God's Mercy to those that Cry (Box 1)
  - God's Providence (Box 1)
  - God's Providence of Doing and Permitting Founded on Contingency (Box 1)
  - The Great Deliverance (Box 1)
  - The Great Promise (Box 1)
  - Healing for the Nations (Box 1)
  - Heaven (Box 1)
  - Help only in God (Box 1)
  - A Higher Status of Life possible and necessary (Box 1)
  - Honest Failure (Box 1)
  - How God is Known (Box 1)
  - House of Prayer (Box 1)
  - Human Happiness (Box 1)
  - The Hurt of my People (Box 1)
  - Immortality (Box 1)
  - Impudence (Box 1)
  - The Influence of the Dead upon the Living and the Living upon the Dead (Box 1)
  - Instant in Season (Box 1)
  - Job (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Judgements of God (Box 1)
  - Keeping the Heart (Box 1)
  - The Kingdom of Christ, 3 versions (Box 1)
  - The Lamb of God (Box 1)
  - The Last Judgment (Box 1)
  - Laying up Treasures (Box 1)
  - Let out the Light (Box 1)
  - Life in the Light of the Gospel (Box 1)
  - Life of the Spirit (Box 1)
  - Love, the only improving power (Box 1)
  - The Magna Charta (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Man with enough (Box 1)
  - The Manifestations of the Spirit (Box 1)
  - Methodism (Box 1)
  - The Mission of Christ (Box 1)
  - Mutual Help (Box 1)
  - Necessity and Sources of Regeneration (Box 1)
  - Necessity and Atonement (Box 1)
  - Obligation to return Favors (Box 1)
  - Our Father (Box 1)
  - Our Natural Character (Box 1)
  - Our Value to God (Box 1)
  - Parental Duties (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Paul's Position (Box 1)
  - The Pecuniary part of Religion (Box 1)
  - Philanthropy (Box 1)
  - The Philosophy of Experience (Box 1)
  - A Plea for Missions (Box 1)
  - Power of the Gospel (Box 1)
  - Praise, A Religious Duty (Box 1)
  - The Praise of Men (Box 1)
  - Prayer and Faith (Box 1)
  - Prayers (Box 1)
  - Preliminary Sufferings of Christ (Box 1)
  - The Prodigal (Box 1)
  - The Profit of Church Membership (Box 1)
  - Proof of the Divinity of Christ (Box 1)
  - The Prospects of Praying, Believing Man (Box 1)
  - Proud Looks (Box 1)
  - Proverbs.... (Box 1)
  - Proving the Heart (Box 1)
  - Prudence (Box 1)
  - The Publican (Box 1)
  - The Ransomed of the Lord (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rebuilding the Temple (Box 1)
  - Reformation (Box 1)
  - Reproof (Box 1)
  - Regeneration (Box 1)
  - Religion is satisfactory the soul (Box 1)
  - Resisting Evil (Box 1)
  - Resisting the Devil (Box 1)
  - The Resurrection of Christ (Box 1)
  - Retribution (Box 1)
  - The Salvation of God (Box 1)
  - Satan... (Box 1)
  - Saving Sinners (Box 1)
  - Scenes in the Future (Box 1)
  - Self Denyal and the Cup (Box 1)
  - The Sinner cannot comprehend his own estate (Box 1)
  - The Sinner destroys God (Box 1)
  - The Sinner's controversy with God (Box 1)
  - Sitting together in heavenly places (Box 1)
  - The Social Estate (Box 1)
  - The Songs of the Temple (Box 1)
  - The Spiritual Conflict (Box 1)
  - The Stature of Christ (Box 1)
  - Straight Paths (Box 1)
  - The Sufferings of Christ (Box 1)
  - Sunday School Lecture (Box 1)
  - Taking the Kingdom (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Terms of Discipleship (Box 1)
  - Testing the Trees (Box 1)
  - True Worshippers (Box 1)
  - Trusting in God (Box 1)
  - Trusting in the Lord (Box 1)
  - Unfaltering Trust (Box 1)
  - The Unspeakable Gift (Box 1)
  - Victory of Sin (Box 1)
  - Waiting for the Holy Spirit (Box 1)
  - The Way of the Lord (Box 1)
  - Weeping is brief (Box 1)
  - We see Darkly (Box 1)
  - What shall I do (Box 1)
  - The Whole Christian (Box 1)
  - The Will of the Lord (Box 1)
  - The Word of the Lord (Box 1)
  - Working for the Multitude (Box 1)
  - Wounded in the house of our friends (Box 1)
  - Yielding to the Will of God (Box 1)
  - Incomplete Sermons (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Funeral Sermons (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sermons - Volumes [Old catalog Nos. 794-803] (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
  - Sermons - Volumes [Old catalog Nos. 804-806, Sketchbook, 1880] (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Dedications, 1882. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes transcript of a speech given by Craven at dedicatory celebrations of a cotton factory in Concord, North Carolina.
  - Education. (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    Speeches given on the topic of education -- normal schools, collegiate education, female education, testing, and scholarships.
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, South. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Topics include unity within the church, and the centennial of the Methodist Church.
  - Fragments of addresses given by Craven. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Topics include education, labor problems, and the Masonic rites and creeds.
- Diaries, 1845-1874
  Arrangement: chronological.
  Although the diaries span the years of 1845-1874, entries do not appear for every year. A partial transcript has been made for a particularly detailed section of Craven's 1868 diary. Handwritten portions of diaries from 1845 and 1855 also are included. The volumes date from the years 1861 (2 volumes), 1868, 1869, 1871, and 1874. These volumes are pocketsize, and some contain ideas for sermons, notes and comments on the weather, farming, preaching, Methodist conferences, and the state of the institution. Also included in this series is a short diary which was kept in 1867 by Craven's eldest daughter, Emma L. Craven. An undated memoranda notebook kept by Braxton Craven is also present.
  - Diaries (Box 2, Folder 30-34)
- Legal and Financial Papers, 1850-1882
  Arrangement: Legal papers alphabetical by topic; financial papers chronological.
  Personal legal papers primarily dealing with transactions of land and money to and from Craven. Topics include receipts, letters of guardianship for orphans, last wills and testaments, indentures, petitions, deeds and legal disputes in which Craven was involved While this series does span the years of 1850-1882, it does not include material from all years. Financial material pertains to the personal finances of Braxton Craven with some items related to the Craven family. Topics in this series include receipts, inventories, promissory notes, and bank ledgers. Also in this collection, are two ledgers (1872-1875) from the Shaw and Company Store, of which Braxton Craven was a partner.
  - Legal Papers (Box 2, Folder 35-44)
  - Financial Papers (Box 2, Folder 45-54)
- Teaching Materials, 1850-1882
  Arrangement: alphabetical; student papers chronological
  Notes from lectures given by Craven, class lists and grade books, and outlines of instruction. The lecture notes have become confused and are roughly arranged alphabetically by subject. It is difficult to ascertain whether these lectures were given at the Union Institute, Normal College or Trinity College. The class lists and grade books are from classes that Craven personally taught and are not for the entire College. The outlines of instruction are summaries of the classes which Craven was teaching during 1850.
  The series also includes student papers and essays, including valedictory and salutatory speeches delivered at Trinity College in 1872 and 1873. There is also a bound volume of 15 graduation speeches from class of 1880. Topics include industrial waste, the Confederate States of America, success, time, music, government, and philosophy. Some fragments of student papers are present.
  - Lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 55-93)
    - Aesthetics (Box 3)
    - Astronomy (Box 3)
    - Beauty (Box 3)
    - Botany (Box 3)
    - Chemistry (Box 3)
    - Education (Box 3)
    - Elocution (Box 3)
    - Fine Arts (Box 3)
    - Geology (Box 3)
    - Government (Box 3)
    - Latin (Box 3)
    - Law (Box 3)
    - Logic (Box 3)
    - Mathematics (Box 3)
    - Mineralogy (Box 3)
    - Natural Science (Box 3)
    - Philosophy (Box 3)
    - Psychology (Box 3)
    - Rhetoric (Box 4, Folder 94-97)
    - Theology (Box 4)
    - Zoology (Box 4)
  - Class lists and grade books, 1850-1882 (Box 4, Folder 98-99)
  - Outlines of instruction, 1850 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Student papers, 1840-1872 (Box 4, Folder 101-103)
- Masonic Papers, undated
  Arrangement: None
  Papers pertaining to the Order of the Masons, of which Craven was a member. Trinity College also had its own Lodge. Included within this series are bylaws of the Trinity Lodge, minutes of meetings, copies of Master Mason's Certificates, and a partial list of members.
  - Masonic papers (Box 4, Folder 104-105)
- Methodist Episcopal Church South, undated
  This series documents Braxton Craven's involvement with the Methodist Episcopal Church South. Included in this series is a roll book of the North Carolina Conference of the Methodist Church, of which Craven was secretary (ca. 1870s). Inside the book are provisions for lay and clerical delegates.
  - Methodist Episcopal Church South (Box 4, Folder 106-107)
- Photographs and Portraits, 1840-1880
  Primarily formal portraits of Braxton Craven with some images of Craven's family, his wife, Irene L Craven, and his tombstone in Trinity, North Carolina. Formats include tintype, ambrotype, engraving, and silhouette.
  - Photographs and portraits (Box 4, Folder 108-109)
- Bibles, 1839, 1970
  This Hebrew Bible was printed in Germany in 1839 and was the property of Braxton Craven. Craven's daughter gave it to the Reverend B.F. Hargett, after her father's death. Hargett gave the Bible to the Reverend Wilbur G. McFarland, who died in 1955.
  - Bible, 1839 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Bible, 1970 (Box 9)
    Caricatures of Braxton Craven are on the rear paste-down and fly-leaf.
- Student Account Books, Food Allocation, and Scrapbooks, 1856-1876
  Scope and Contents
  Included are account books accounts of student tuition, bible, book, boarding fees, paper, and ink purchases. Several volumes include the signatures of students. Roll books contain students' names, courses, attendance, assignments, and grades.
  - Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, 1856-1857 (Box 6)
  - Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, 1858-1866 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook of Clippings of Advice, Poetry, and Prayers, 1860 (Box 6)
    Scrapbook looks to have been created from a notebook where writing is visible in spaces between the clippings. One page near the end includes minutes from a meeting of the Jollie Club on January 26, 1870.
  - Student Roll Book, with Grades and Inserted Absence Slips, 1860-1861 (Box 7)
  - Student Roll Book with Grades and Attendance, 1860-1861 (Box 7)
  - Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, with Class Lists, 1860-1863 (Box 7)
  - Accounts of Food Allotments, and Student Roll Book, with Grades, 1864-1869 (Box 7)
    First eighteen pages of book include accounting of women and children, and their amounts of bacon, meal, beef, and salt possibly used during the Civil War. Remainder of book includes a student roll book with grades.
  - Student Roll Book, and Sunday School Attendance, 1875-1876 (Box 7)
- Oversize materials
  - Sermons (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Class Lecture Notes (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Portrait (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Framed box containing: 1859 slave contract signed by Braxton Craven; 1880 promissory note signed by Craven; undated carte de viste of Craven (photo by Rufus Morgan); pocket pistol dated 1845. (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook of "interesting love stories" clipped from serial publications, 19th century (Box 10)